um so this is a a group of sutas that
are basically on the same talking about
the same topic the first one isaya B of
5es number 151
um so it says because someone with five
qualities is unable to enter the short
path in regard to beneficial qualities
even when listening to the true teaching
what five they discredit The Talk The
Speaker or themselves they listen with a
scattered and distracted mind and they
attend not through the origin which is
ionara someone with these five qualities
is unable to enter the sure path in
regard to beneficial qualities even when
listening to the true teaching and it
says someone five qualities is able to
enter the sh path and to beneficial
qualities when they have the opposite
qualities so they don't discredit the
top the speaker or themselves they
listen with an unscattered and unified
mind and they attend through the origin
so
Yara and
uh so maybe we can start with that one
because the other two have
sort of a similar structure but those
five things are
slightly vared so
yeah um first of
[Music] all we should probably clarify what does
all we should probably clarify what does
it mean to enter the short path in
regard to beneficial
qualities because uh you know it's not
just uh it it shouldn't be minimized into
uh it it shouldn't be minimized into
just like oh I now I agree with the
Buddhist teaching or something because
or or even I took Refuge because there
were many instances in the SAS of people
who factually said I I take refuge in
the Buddha
damasa but they weren't in the sure
path in in the wholesome qualities which
means they were not um guaranteed to
become our Huns because they didn't get
the right view yeah so that's basically
also like the answer like yeah like that
particular phrase is a somewhat
technical term but I take it to mean the
first of the eight kinds of individuals
of beings yeah because then you know you
can to some
extent have like as it says a Yara so
then even if you don't have the other
four uh and you think the Buddha is the
greatest and you have like total
conviction but you don't have that yisa
recognition of where this teaching
actually applies then then yeah you will
as the budha said there there's the the
one who is which means like all he can
do is is learn the
phrases learn the kind of teachings and
recite them and kind of talk about them
but not actually there's no actual
purification taking place because as we
often say that right level hasn't been
discerned where those two teachings
actually apply yeah so what would be
some of the most common ways that you
know even though as it does someone
would be listening to the true teaching
reading the suas and what not uh that
they would be attending
a even in like just a very basic way
uhhuh uh
yes like of
Restraint of course yeah that would be
causing it but but like what would be
the more directly speaking like like
while you are listening to someone else
yeah so what reasons why kind of
Frameworks of thought that you would have yeah that
of thought that you would have yeah that
would prevent you
from understanding seeing it as um
explanation yeah
so
even more kind of generally than that
yeah so you see if one only listens to
and you're assuming that the that the
speaker that the other person is
actually proclaiming true Dharma and and
knows what he's talking about so
everyone is hearing those words but is
just attending to those words meaning it
stays completely external right and you
do not let's say simultaneously with
what you hear also observe all your own
reactions to what you hear or somebody
uses a certain word and you immediately
connected with oh yeah that other person
has said the same thing or I read that
in a book a year ago therefore well this
actually going to be the next one but
therefore I have already understood it
right that mental
movement um is almost completely taken
for granted it goes so quickly so either
one stays completely on the external
level and doesn't actually see where
those words are supposed to land
internally um so the intermediate step
is to have those let's say both both
domains um to attend to them both at the
same time yeah so so it put it in a more
even more simple term that you don't see
that this dama is about you yeah you
could put like that yeah self-reflexive
exactly yeah it's about you it's not
about cuz you know there are infinite
ways that you can proliferate into like
oh yeah that you know how they would
connected with all the science this is
the same thing as the scientists are
saying that's level of wrong views now
interfering exactly or then like trying
to find parallels between this school
and that school and and this and that
yeah and um even with the sutas actually
um you know there's now the the whole
kind of early Buddhist movement which is
has its positives obviously because you
know disregarding a lot of the stuff
that came later and muddles the actual
message but then you can see the same
kind of a aiso attitude remains in the
form of now like oh this uh you know
there has no parallel in the Chinese or
then you know studying it that kind of
that's actually another practical way in
which you can tell that you are
attending not from the origin that is uh
this attitude of comparison like if if
you find that you are comparing what you
hear with something else that means that
that you have already externalized the
message into an object that you can sort
of put in front of you and then compare
it with something else and meanwhile you
stay safely out of the equation because
you are just concerned with finding the
connections there whereas the whole
message should be 90° the way exactly so
you need to be comparing it with
yourself so I talking Buddha as always
we be talking about GRE diversion and
delusion do I have those qualities to
what extent do I have those
qualities um so that that that would be
a basic because I mean obviously this is
not like not talking about a super kind
of accur accurate discernment of of you
know final imp impermanence and not self
or something because it's just saying oh
it's just the sure path in regard to
beneficial quality so it's the very
start of a
path but it's so fundamental that you
know if you skip that part then even if
later on you get all the information
about anata and all this and that it's
coming from the wrong direction
yeah and the SW Maybe you can say the uh
I mean I have uh learned it like this
froma when he was emphasizing on the
subjective uh compared to the objective
which is just uh keeping the formations
yes arms length yeah yeah actually
that's that's one thing because um often
it's thought like okay so self has to be
abandoned kind of message of the Bush
teaching so then that means subjectivity
has to be destroyed you have to be
perfectly objective and that's when this
sort of message comes in like yeah
ironically like that's completely the
opposite of what it's saying you take
yourself out of the equation you don't
consider like you know your mental
States your liabilities it's just this
blank present moment we're all in the
same thing these impersonal kind of
sensation watching or something like
that and uh the the essence of like
craving my craving that I act out of you
know that part is is completely
undressed yeah and if it would be on
that level then an average well-trained
scientist we would have some reports
that that they entered that path of
security inome States yeah because
perfectly objective individual then yeah
would be would be in the position to
realize the other so so you have to
start by taking it personally ironically
and from within that subjective attitude
as you mentioned that is where the
purification needs to happen if you skip
that first step you basically don't even
start and actually the it always says
when somebody would start practice and
you know become a monk it would say uh
The Clansman realizes that he's pray to
suffering he's subject to suffering so
he's not just like trying in that
impersonal manner like oh I want to find
out whether this have this curiosity
want to find out whether this teaching
is is true or not in that kind of imp
personal sense so that then I can kind
of make the comparisons with the other
ones no no it's I am pray to suffering
and I need to find a solution for this
and that leads to the well it was
actually the previous one but we skipped
on to the last one um that's that's then
when you would be kind of discrediting
the speaker and the talk and and because
um
if you don't have the context of you
know imagine you're looking for a cure
for a
disease and then if you don't keep that
in mind you don't keep that keep that as
as your background of okay this is what
I'm going to this doctor then you will
be putting first a bunch all whole sets
of other things like oh his attitude the
way he talks secondary kind of
considerations and you'll be finding
fault with I mean infinite amount of
things like um oh why why did he spend
such such year this amount of years in
medical school instead of this other
amount of years like random things you
could start finding fault with yeah oh I
don't like the way he talk I don't like
the way he looks he he comports himself
all these external things that that so
you can notice that and so it's okay to
not like it but it's but that's not the
criteria for dismissing the validity of
the message yeah so because then again
like if you have that urgency to find
the way out of
suffering it it should be pretty clear
to you that if you allow yourself to use
the criteria that you're used to to
determine what is worth following or not
you're most likely going to you know
pass over yeah what's what was the true
teaching so basically you have nothing
to gain from from that kind of attitude
of finding fault because with it with
the speaker with the talk because it's
not going to help you even if it's wrong
actually it's not going to help you um
actually understand why it's wrong it's
going to be just like oh I dismiss it
again out of all these bunch of other
reasons but uh you wouldn't be able to
to kind of come up with a coherent
explanation of you know it's I see for
myself why this doesn't solve the
problem that I'm trying to solve mhm why
it do need to fre yeah so somebody might
be giving a factually wrong message and
it is and to recognize a wrong view as
wrong view is valid but what is not
valid is to have the mental state that
is looking for faults in the speaker or
the message those are two different
things and you don't need to have that
mental attitude in order to see that
something fact doesn't add up yeah
exactly as the Buddha said the criticism
should be always about the
view and it should shouldn't be about
the person yeah so
and the one that says disparaging
themselves well that's why it says that
if
um the the starting point of everything
is is virtue and it says when somebody's
not establishing virtue they will not be
free from regrets mhm so that's the
that's the there was a case of that King
who was the the king who murdered the
was the the king who murdered the
previous King who was his father yes and
then uh danaya too and then the Buddha
was kind of telling him the whole DH
basically explained to him and then at
the end of it he said oh If he if he
hadn't killed his father he would have
gained the right view right there but
he's now broken because of what he did
like he cannot be that remorse he cannot
kind of grow out of it anymore because
it's so kind of heavy so then looking in
the direction again turning the dhama
into that personal Dimension like of
great verion and delusion is wrong and
look what I
diduh then that that thought would be so
unbearable that you know they wouldn't
be able to kind of again apply that un s
um and see oh yeah I have to actually
feel ashamed about this so then yeah
that that's why he wouldn't have been
able to get the right view because to
some extent uh even if there wasn't like that
extent uh even if there wasn't like that
kind of um overly coarse external
scientific objective attitude that
people might have today still he had to
kind of keep it at arms length to some
degree so as to not feel the weights of
his
responsibility so that's that's in a
sense why you need to be establishment
virtue because you know yeah it might
not be like that might have stopped
be like that might have stopped
him butth you don't know for you maybe
something even lesser than that could be
what stops you that such that deep down
you still dispar discredit yourself like
you still have that sense of remorse on
account of something that you know is
wrong and yeah you would maybe not even
be fully aware of it because that's how
these things work you cover them up and
uh you don't want to admit them so yeah
so then you have to go stronger in order
to be with that and then that might
still be an opportunity to actually hear
the message yeah yes it says the only
things that categorically stop everyone
from understanding dama is is like
killing your father mhm which is what he
did killing your mother um shedding the
intentionally shedding the blood
ofata violating a viony and killing an
killing an AR
yeah yeah so assuming that that's now
not the case we can continue yeah
yeah so
um yeah so the the second one says the
same thing and the five qualities are
Again discredit The Talk The Speaker or
themselves they're witless dull and
stupid and the fifth one which is the
most interesting one they think they
understand what they don't understand
yeah someone with these five qualities
is unable to enter the short path in
regard to beneficial qualities even when
this true teaching
so the third one is they listen to the
teaching with a h hostile fault finding
mind they're antagonistic to the teacher
planning to attack them they're wless
dull and stupid and again they don't
understand what they think they
understand what they don't
understand yeah I think attack there is
like verbal like you just want to argue
have debates and and basically wanna wna
prove your own points which just somewh
I want it because if that would be right
you would suffer yeah so see you you are
Imagine like you go to this doctor and
he's telling you the treatment and
you're trying to tell him what the
treatment is yeah that's so then that
means like oh you're not even honest
about the fact that you are sick yeah
and that you don't know the way out so
but then yeah you well that ties in was
saying oh he thinks he understands what
he doesn't actually understand
and that would be probably one of the
most prevalent um attitudes especially
again because of the I mean all of it
ties in together like because of this
whole objective attitude that you know
you just gather this information and
then you know everybody and other
Buddhists say the same thing and you
agree and that's that's kind of it mhm and
and that's that's kind of it mhm and
then oh I understood yeah or it makes
sense intellectually but we did talk on
how even the right ideas are not
necessarily Insight so yeah you do need
to have the right ideas and the right
Concepts you need to think in the right
categories but it's a mistake to stop on
that level and not now go
further and I think also like
um like just during that like I I can
see that like the kind of tendency will
be okay okay so then I don't understand
but like this kind of I don't understand
can become what I think I do understand
in order to not feel the weight of it
like like it's not enough to say like
okay I don't understand like I should we
were talking about that a little bit the
other day like I should take on like if
I really kind of acknowledge the fact
that I don't understand I should act as
if I don't understand and not starting
to kind of like okay don't understand
but still I'm doing this I'm doing that
I'm doing that it kind of doesn't go
together and I think Med was kind of
nice but more kind of this attitude of
taking like I don't understand in order
to not feel the pressure of Doubt but
actually like this recognition of like I
don't understand it's not not
necessarily a pleasant things to
organize for on yeah that that it
doesn't become like an excuse
for just doing oh okay I don't
understand so I just do whatever hoping
that understanding will magically arise
M uh so
yeah I don't understand and partially
that's probably because of things I
myself am doing so then that should feel
again you should feel the responsibility
for that so because would have said yeah
I mean uh uh fundamentally beings are
owners of their actions and you know all
of
the great diversion and delusion that
you've accumulated if even if you don't
remember all the things that you did
fundamentally at that time you chose to
do those things MH so um um the same way
yeah you have to realize you don't
understand it's because of not
necessarily because of things you're
doing did in the past but because now
that you have an option to go in a
different direction you still
don't you might you might be you know
agreeing again with with these external
explanations of dhama and whatnot but
okay when it comes down to do you act as
if craving is the root of suffering do
you live that view mhm or or is it just
kind of um an idea disconnected from
your daily life and and and you you can
even see that you know this is what the
Buddha is saying would lead to entering
that short path in regard to skillful
qualities whereas usually it would be
like the assumption would be uh again
like a Mindless practice with meditation
where indeed you would be assuming you
understand what you don't understand
because oh I just do this I don't need
to understand for myself you know what
is wholesome what is UN wholesome I
assume that this is already wholesome in
and of itself and I just do it but see
none of this that that's never mentioned
here like the Buddha doesn't say you
will fail to understand what you you
fail to understand the dhama because
you're not sufficiently skilled in that
cuz cuz people usually assume okay yeah
I I know I kind of know the dharm you
because I've been reading the sutas and
you know practicing for God knows how
many years but uh because I haven't
meditated enough or consistently enough
or or long enough Retreat yeah I didn't
I haven't had that kind of special
Insight that kind of experiential
recognition of these things that I
already in see that's the mistake yeah
the confirmation that the method is
Right hasn't arrived yet whereas
actually the method itself is to
understand what the problem is exactly
so instead of having that expect a you
should see oh no
wait am I even right in assuming that
this is the practice yes so yeah but
that's now going to be unpleasant
because you cannot now just disappear in
your practice for another hour you need
to now need to question yeah that very
practice so a lot of this boils down to
the ability to um allow doubt to be present
ability to um allow doubt to be present
and to make that your vehicle until you
find that which you cannot out basically
yeah because that is in every single case
because that is in every single case
when you read the sutas would led to
somebody getting the right View and it's
described there it's
Yara and the utterance of another so
it's not like because yeah literally the
way it's presented is like no no you may
not have heard anything no Ence of
another no nothing you just do this boom
you get
it but uh no clearly here it's saying if
you have these attitudes that kind of
obstruct your right acceptance of what yes
your right acceptance of what yes
initially is just information mhm then
uh you will not get to understand that
information and the nature of
understanding if you think about it it's
like you know what what is it that
determines whether you understand some
kind of mathematical theorem or
something like is it that oh no no I
understand it
but I still need to get
the experience of something in order to
understand it no you like you know that
you don't understand it or if you
understand it you know that you do
understand it yeah so there's nothing
more mystical about uh understanding the
foral truths so what would be the
measure cuz see of course I say that and
then it sounds like oh so you're saying
it's just intellectual kind of uh
recognition the of of things that are
exist but no because how would you know
that you actually understood the way out
of suffer yeah or that there isn't or or
you see yes or you might have been going
in the right direction and see some
benefit but you didn't go far enough
yeah right so but yeah how would you know
right so but yeah how would you know
that your understanding of foral truth
that yes everybody has to some extent
because you know theyve been reading the
sutas how do you know that that's how
would you disting that
between uh let's say insight and and
understanding given that it's not just
some experience that because experiences
are impermanent doesn't mean anything
yeah yeah let's say between ideas and
and insight yeah yeah yeah so idea will
be like the theoretical kind of thinking
and the Insight will be like the direct
recognition of oh that's how it is yeah
but then but then yeah so how would
you cuz even yeah even an experience
magical experience you might have had in
your meditation that doesn't mean you
understood for of truths if we take it
from this criteria then hinting at
um maybe like I just just I think um
will be like if I'm in a kind of
situation where I find myself
suffering like I don't have to explain
myself why is that happening I kind of
recognize it and I I know kind of why is
that there yeah but see then even saying why
there yeah but see then even saying why
is that there that could mean like psych
psychologization of like oh yeah it's
because the Consciousness is like this
and then this happens and people start
talking about mind moments or whatever
so what would be like I me because what
are the for of truths it's not just
knowing what the problem is
understand the question so like how how
do you know that you that you have fully
understood the formable truths or
sufficiently let say yeah sufficiently
the formable truth so that it's not an
idea because people kind have the idea
craving is suffering which is a right
idea but that doesn't mean that there is
now no suffering anymore it's just an
idea and uh the answer to your question
is in that
direction I think you're already
yeah yeah so
basically if there is still suffering
yeah it doesn't matter if you have to
explain it if you have
to if you have to um review the
information that you gain to kind of
feel at ease MH that's is management
again exactly so the the measure
for actual understanding
understanding yeah it is kind of
something you would be able to explain
to somebody else so it's not that it's
some kind of mystical like oh I know it
but I can't explain it yeah yeah or it
is a nameless truth or it cannot be put
into words which is ual mystifications
exactly no no it is something you can
you can explain which is what the Buddha
was doing the entire
time but at the same
time the the Practical confirmation of
it is that you don't suffer factually
and and that is what um that's what
makes it
experiential U not not some kind of
magical Insight or again mystical s oh I
saw the final truth no no it is like
throughout your day when you encounter
things that confine your mind and make
it feel kind of like uh burdened and
weighed down are you affected
down are you affected
mhm yeah
so then then you get to see whether it's
just information or whether it's um
actually understanding the way out of
suffering and again yeah it's not about
just using the information to kind of
manage the suffering after the fact
because from that point of view I mean
millions of teachings can do that U you
just convince yourself that God loves
you or something and that has exactly
the same effect so dama is
the only teaching that doesn't require
even that it's suffering not arising in
the first
place so you say when the mind is still
we down constricted I guess by whatever
occurring experience painful situation
yes but would that the Nots suffering
part would that be on account of having
Tamed trained the mind that then would not
trained the mind that then would not
be bothering
you or would the Mind still be kicking
while you would not
be well that's what that's the that's
the final Insight that would had like
there were other atics and brahmans that
that would factually teach The Taming of
the mind but uh with the the only one
who actually taught the complete
transcending of the appropriation was
the budha so then that's why even when
yeah your mind factually that actually
that's that's a that's quite a a good
distinction between because yeah you
could even use uh The Virtue as a form
of management to some degree I mean it's
the right management that will help you
um understand them like without without
virtue there giving no dma but
fundamentally as the Buddha said the
dhma is not virt so then you went to
realize oh is it yeah is it is it that I
suffer that I'm free from suffering only
because I'm kind of uh so withdrawn from
all these things from you know sense
objects and sensuality in in the right
way or is it because even if I were to
completely just you know let go of the
practice then nothing would arise
obviously if you had developed yourself
properly you wouldn't be able to do
certain things anymore as the Buddha
said cannot break the the precepts and
cannot break celibacy so but yeah then
that's why um fundamentally as the
Buddha said uh somebody and which you
could say is like the mind being tamed
or being
pliable um that's not the
hardwood of of the teaching it's like
irreversible Liberation which is he call like the
Liberation which is he call like the
unshakable liberation of the mind that
is the essence of so that is really the
final non-management because as he said
even Buist who obviously would still be
dependent on management to some degree
they could still you know attain the
right kind of some and stuff the problem
is that now the management is like even
of a less like it's not even that it's
not even like taming the mind it's just
ignoring it so that's
why yeah then then then uh it's it's not
even helpful but yes even the right
management uh of of taming the mind in
the right way um that will be
transcended by by the uh understanding
of the formal TRS
so then as to say they would um like the
the arand would continue practicing only
for kind of a pleasant biting here and
now or for kind of a example for future
Generations but not because it's
necessary like like a a who hasn't
understood the that factual sensation be
like no no no I have to keep doing this forever for